{"tossups": [{"question": "This woman employed the Munshi Abdul Karim as an Urdu teacher, and she described her grandson, William, as possessing \"little heart and tact.\" This person was advised in her early rule by Lord Melbourne, before forming a longtime friendship with Prime Minister Benjamin Disraeli. The Crystal Palace Exhibition was the brainchild of this ruler's husband, Albert. For ten points, name this long-reigning monarch, who presided over much of nineteenth-century Britain.", "answer": "Queen <b><u>Victoria</u></b> (or Alexandrina <b><u>Victoria</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One theory about this event claimed Judah P. Benjamin perpetrated it by enlisting the help of the Rothschild banking family from Europe. Police officer John Frederick Parker's abandonment of his post to grab a drink made this event possible. Major Rathbone was stabbed with a dagger during this event, shortly before a man shouted \"Sic Semper Tyrannus\" during a performance of <em>Our American Cousin</em>. John Wilkes Booth perpetrated, for ten points, what killing of the sixteenth president?", "answer": "The Abraham <b><u>Lincoln Assassination</u></b> in Ford's Theater (accept word forms and descriptions involving the killing of <b><u>Lincoln</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A character in this short story passes British spy Major Andre\u2019s tree and loses his horse Gunpowder\u2019s saddle after a party in Tarry Town. In this story, Katrina Van Tassel marries Brom Bones, who laughs when a crushed pumpkin is found near where a schoolteacher, Ichabod Crane, has vanished while being chased by a Galloping Hessian. For ten points, name this short story by Washington Irving in which the title location is haunted by the Headless Horseman.", "answer": "\"The <b><u>Legend of Sleepy Hollow</u></b>\" (do not accept or prompt on \"Tale of Sleepy Hollow\")", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "The Four Books and Five Classics are the authoritative texts of this man's philosophy, one of the so-called Hundred Schools of Thought. The first of this man's Five Constants is <em>r\u00e9n</em>, or \"humaneness.\" This man believed that the emperor's Mandate of Heaven must be subject to absolute moral principles, including virtues like filial piety. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese philosopher known for his interpretation of the Golden Rule.", "answer": "<b><u>Confucius</u></b> (accept <b><u>K\u01d2ng F\u016bz\u01d0</u></b>; or <b><u>Kongzi</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A loan from this nation's Erlanger & Co. allowed the Confederacy to build ironclads as blockade runners. Three emissaries from this nation requested bribes from U.S. diplomats before allowing negotiations with Talleyrand in the XYZ Affair. The U.S. fought the Quasi-War with this nation, who earlier sent armed forces to the Thirteen Colonies during the Yorktown campaign. The Louisiana colony was sold to the United States by, for ten points, what European country?", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>France</u></b> (or Royaume de <b><u>France</u></b>; accept Republic of <b><u>France</u></b>; or <b><u>French</u></b> First Republic; or R\u00e9publique <b><u>Fran\u00e7aise</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The building of this structure was supervised by Ustad Ahmad Lahauri, who also laid the foundations of the Red Fort. This building, whose name is derived from Persian, was ordered by an emperor who was put under house arrest by his successor, Aurangzeb [[ow-RAHNG-zeb]]. This building was originally constructed to house the tomb of Mumtaz. For ten points, name this enormous mausoleum in Agra, India, constructed by Shah Jahan.", "answer": "<b><u>Taj Mahal</u></b> (or <b><u>Rauza-i Munawwara</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "While en route to Western Europe, this man had 4,000 <em>denarii</em> seized in the port of Trebizond, retaining some of his wealth by sewing precious stones into his coat. With Rustichello da Pisa, this man published his travelogue under the title <em>Book of the Marvels of</em> <em>the World</em>. That work describes this man's trip to the palace of Xanadu [[ZAN-ah-doo]] and his travels along the Silk Road. For ten points, name this Venetian merchant who explored the Far East and served Kublai Khan.", "answer": "Marco <b><u>Polo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Various speeches by this man were mixed with modern musical accompaniment by progressive rocker Giulio Neroni in the album <em>Wake Up!</em> Referencing the \"calming of the storm\" in the Book of Mark, this man gave an <em>Urbi et Orbi</em> address in the wake of the COVID-19 pandemic. The 2021 Synod of Bishops was called by this figure following news of an abuse scandal in France. Jorge Bergoglio [[behr-GOH-lyoh]] is the birth name of, for ten points, what pope from Argentina?", "answer": "Pope <b><u>Francis</u></b> (accept <b><u>Francis</u></b> I; accept Jorge <b><u>Bergoglio</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Verrocchio [[veh-ROH-kyoh]] depicted this figure in bronze following his most famous action, while Bernini sculpted a marble statue of this man during that same violent action. Donatello's sculpture of this figure was the first freestanding nude since antiquity, and another depiction of this hero has an oversized head to appear proportional from below. For ten points, name this Biblical king who was depicted in a marble sculpture by Michelangelo before he slays Goliath.", "answer": "<b><u>David</u></b> (or <b><u>Davit</u></b>; accept <b><u>Daud</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In modern Spain, this general created a makeshift bridge to cross the Baetis [[BAY-tiss]] River to win the Battle of Munda. Tribes like the Bibroci [[bee-BROH-kee]] and the Ancalites united around Cassibelanus [[cah-see-beh-LAH-nus]] in a failed attempt to repel this man's invasion of Britannia. This writer of <em>De Bello Gallico</em> defeated and captured the King Vercingetorix [[ver-sin-GEH-toh-riks]] during the Siege of Alesia. The Rubicon was crossed by, for ten points, what Roman dictator?", "answer": "Gaius <b><u>Julius Caesar</u></b> (prompt on \"Caesar\" alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This journalist wrote for the newspaper <em>Avanti!</em>, but during World War One abandoned both it and his country's Socialist Party. This prime minister's followers, sometimes dubbed \"Squadristis,\" were known as the Black Shirts. Declaring himself \"Il Duce,\" [[eel-DOO-cheh]] this man aligned with Nazi Germany, though his armed forces failed to secure North Africa or stop the Allied invasion of Sicily. For ten points, name this leader of Italy during most of World War Two.", "answer": "Benito <b><u>Mussolini</u></b> (or Benito Amilcare Andrea <b><u>Mussolini</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Practitioners of the Kumbhi Mela, a pilgrimage to this site, were attacked by the British during the seizure of Allahabad during the Sepoy Mutiny. The capital of the Nanda empire, Pataliputra [[pah-tah-lee-POO-trah]], was founded where this river meets the Son. Varanasi lies on this river, and Delhi lies on its second-largest tributary, the Yamuna. A namesake \"Action Plan\" by Rajiv Gandhi failed to clean-up, for ten points, which heavily polluted river in the eastern Indian sub-continent?", "answer": "<b><u>Ganges</u></b> River (or the <b><u>Ganga</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A cavalry commander with this last name surprised the namesake commander in Pyle's Massacre while campaigning with Francis Marion's Carolina militia. A head of the Army of Northern Virginia with this last name repelled McClellan's Peninsula Campaign and fought the Battle of Antietam. That man with this last name formally surrendered to Ulysses S. Grant at Appomattox Courthouse. Military officers \"Light-Horse Harry\" and his son Robert E. possessed, for ten points, what last name?", "answer": "<b><u>Lee</u></b> (accept Robert E. <b><u>Lee</u></b> or Henry \"Light-Horse Harry\" <b><u>Lee</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A senator from this U.S. state introduced the Sunshine Protection Act, which aimed to make Daylight Savings year-round. This state's Department of Health fined Leon County 3.5 million dollars for violating this state's anti-vaccine passport laws. Failure to fix major cracks in this state's Champlain Towers led to a deadly 2021 collapse of that condo, killing 97 residents in Surfside. In 2019, Ron DeSantis became governor of, for ten points, what Southern U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Florida</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This entertainer, who openly advocated for the desegregation of Las Vegas casinos, was shamed by the media for performing at the Mafia-organized Havana Conference. Those ties to organized crime led to this singer being removed from the close circle of President Kennedy. With Dean Martin, Sammy Davis Jr., and Joey Bishop, this man formed a group known as \"The Rat Pack.\" The songs \"My Way\" and \"Fly Me to the Moon\" were performed by, for ten points, which Italian-American crooner?", "answer": "Frank <b><u>Sinatra</u></b> (or Francis Albert <b><u>Sinatra</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Robert Haslam rose to prominence in this organization during its involvement</u></b> <b><u>in the Pyramid Lake War. Raymond and Nancy Settle tried to compile a list of (*)</u></b> <b>riders in this organization in </b><em><b>Saddles & Spurs</b></em><b>. During this organization\u2019s eighteen-month run, only six riders died according to the National Park Service. Buffalo Bill Cody (*) </b>worked for, for ten points, what organization that delivered mail from Missouri to California on horseback?", "answer": "<b><u>Pony Express</u></b> (accept Central Overland California and <b><u>Pikes Peak Express</u> </b>Company)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This company briefly purchased Columbia Pictures but sold it to Sony</u></b> <b><u>following the failure of</u> </b><em><b><u>Ishtar</u></b></em><b><u>. Near its headquarters, this company operates a multi-</u><u>storied tourist attraction called the \"World of\" (+)</u> [this company]. Founded by Asa Griggs Candler to sell a namesake drink invented in 1886 by John Pemberton, (*) </b>for ten points, name this multinational beverage corporation based in Atlanta, Georgia, the chief rival of Pepsi.", "answer": "The <b><u>Coca-Cola</u></b> Company (prompt on \"Coke\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the aftermath of this event, the victor fled to St. Simon's Island in Georgia to</u></b> <b><u>hide at Pierce Butler's plantation. The victim of this event supposedly told Dr. David</u></b> <b><u>Hosack he intended to (+)</u> shoot into the ground, and this event occurred in part because one participant opposed the other's 1800 U.S. presidential run. Weehawken, (*) </b>New Jersey was the site of, for ten points, what violent confrontation between the former Secretary of the Treasury and the sitting vice president?", "answer": "<b><u>Burr-Hamilton Duel</u></b> (accept answers describing combat between Aaron <b><u>Burr</u> </b>and Alexander <b><u>Hamilton</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These specific people were banned from working on the Sabbath in the</u></b> <b><u>\"Manifesto of three-day Corvee [[kor-VEH]]\" passed by Paul I. During the \"Forbidden</u></b> <b><u>Years,\" the hardship of the (*)</u> Livonian wars and crop failure led to these specific people losing their right to move from their estate. These people paid a rent known as </b><em><b>obrok</b></em><b> to the landed (*) </b><em>boyars</em> they served. In 1861, Alexander II emancipated, for ten points, what peasant class of Russia?", "answer": "Russian <b><u>Serf</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Krepostnoy Krest'yanin</u></b>; accept <b><u>Peasant</u></b>s before mentioned; prompt on \"Unfree Person\"; do not accept or prompt on \"slave\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this nation, Hezekiah Ochuka was hanged for his leadership of a 1982 coup</u></b> <b><u>attempt, which failed after most of his soldiers got drunk instead of arresting the</u></b> <b><u>sitting president. The White Highlands of this nation were seized during the (+)</u> Mau Mau Uprising, whose participants included Daniel arap Moi and Jomo (*) </b>Kenyatta. Formerly known as British East Africa, for ten points, what nation includes cities such as Mombasa and Nairobi?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Kenya</u></b> (or Jamhuri ya <b><u>Kenya</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Known as</u> </b><em><b><u>heket</u></b></em><b><u> to the Egyptians, this good fills the \"mouth of a perfectly</u></b> <b><u>contented man,\" according to a 23rd century BC proverb. Shorting a customer of this</u></b> <b><u>substance is punishable by (+)</u> drowning per the Code of Hammurabi, and the Sumerians drank a thick version of this beverage through a straw. Cereals like barley and (*) </b>wheat are used to make, for ten points, what ancient alcoholic drink often made at a brewery?", "answer": "<b><u>Beer</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One composer from this modern-day country used a \"sacred minimalist\"</u></b> <b><u>sound that is exemplified by his</u> </b><em><b><u>Symphony of Sorrowful Songs</u></b></em><b><u> and the (*)</u> </b><em><b>Copernican </b><b>Symphony</b></em><b>. Another composer from this country wrote a series of pieces based on music from this country, including mazurkas and polonaises, though he is best known for his \u00e9tudes and the </b><em><b>Minute Waltz</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For ten points, name this home country of Henryk G\u00f3recki and Fr\u00e9d\u00e9ric Chopin [[shoh-PAHN]], who was born in the Duchy of Warsaw.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Poland</u></b> (or Rzeczpospolita <b><u>Polska</u></b>; accept <b><u>Polish</u></b>; accept Second <b><u>Polish</u></b> Republic; prompt on \"Duchy of Warsaw\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>After the Great Flood of 1927 on this body of water, over 200,000 displaced</u></b> <b><u>Black people moved north, joining the Great Migration. The longest (+)</u> levee system in the world was authorized in response to this body overflowing in the most destructive flood in U.S. history. Many downriver parishes in (*) </b>Louisiana were destroyed during the 1927 \"Great Flood\" of, for ten points, what major U.S. river that enters the Gulf of Mexico near New Orleans?", "answer": "<b><u>Mississippi</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's middle name meant \"troublemaker\" in the Xhosa [[KOH-sah]]</u></b> <b><u>language. As a member of his country's Communist Party, this man lived on the</u></b> <b><u>Liliesleaf Farm while heading \"Spear of the Nation.\" (+)</u> In 1964, this man declared \"I Am Prepared to Die\" during the Rivonia Trial. During his country's first free elections in 1994, this man's African (*) </b>National Congress defeated F.W. de Klerk's National Party. For ten points, name this first post-apartheid South African president.", "answer": "Nelson <b><u>Mandela</u></b> (or Nelson Rolihlahla <b><u>Mandela</u></b>; accept Rolihlahla <b><u>Mandela</u></b>; prompt on \"Madiba\" or \"Dalibunga\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}